A Guide to the Russell Sage Foundation records FA015
Rockefeller Archive Center
Russell Sage Foundation records
1879-2002, bulk 1907-2000
1907-2000
Rockefeller Archive Center
Sage, Margaret Olivia Slocum
Russell Sage Foundation
FA015
160.62 Cubic Feet
Arrangement note
This Russell Sage Foundation records are arranged into 3 sub-groups, each with mulitple series thereunder: 1. RSF records, 1885-1983, 2. RSF records, 1974-2002.
A subgroup at the end of the collection is designated for photographs.
Biographical/Historical note
The Russell Sage Foundation was established in 1907 by Margaret Olivia Slocum Sage (1828-1918) as a memorial to her late husband, Russell Sage, the railroad magnate and Wall Street financier. Mrs. Sage's original gift for the Foundation of $10 million was increased in 1918 with a bequest of $5 million.
The mission of the Russell Sage Foundation is the "improvement of social and living conditions in the United States of America." Mrs. Sage placed no restrictions on how this mission was to be fulfilled. She wished the scope of the Russell Sage Foundation to be national, but also requested that special attention be paid to New York City and its environs.
The Russell Sage Foundation received the largest single gift made by Mrs. Sage but she dispensed a total of $35 million between 1907 and her death in 1918. She made most of her contributions in the traditional manner of responding to individual solicitations on a case-by-case basis. Some institutions received a single large gift while others received, for several years, regular gifts of lesser amounts. Mrs. Sage also expressed her support of many organizations, mostly local, in a more symbolic way through gifts of $100 or less, lifetime memberships, or annual patronages.
Between 1907 and 1946, the Russell Sage Foundation focused its attention on improving the quality of living by exposing social problems and proposing and sponsoring practical solutions for those problems. The results of its investigations and field studies were presented in books, pamphlets and articles published by the Russell Sage Foundation.
During this time the Foundation was organized by departments based on fields of research. Included among these departments were Charity Organization, Industrial Studies, Recreation, Surveys and Exhibits, and Statistics. The areas of study included, but were not limited to, public welfare, labor and industrial relations, regional planning, penology, child welfare, and the social work profession. The Russell Sage Foundation also supported existing social agencies and helped establish new agencies to serve previously neglected social concerns.
In 1948, due to declining financial investments and the gradual attrition of its staff, the Russell Sage Foundation underwent a philosophical and structural reorganization. It shifted its focus to basic research in the social and behavioral sciences and the strengthening of social welfare methodology. Structurally, it discontinued its specialized departments and created a coordinated central staff of professional personnel. Much of the work could then be carried out by individuals hired temporarily for specific projects. The Russell Sage Foundation presently continues in this role.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted are noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
File Plan
Former Classification: VI
Related Archival Materials note
Oversized Material; Card Files; 35 mm Film; Annual Reports; and Newsletters.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Russell Sage Foundation donated its records to the Rockefeller Archive Center in 1985.
Scope and Contents
The Russell Sage Foundation records consist of correspondence, office files, reports, grant proposals, publications, photographs, and some digital media materials documenting the Foundation's activities during the years 1879-2002, with the bulk of the material from 1907-2000.
Charities; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Philanthropy -- United States; New York (N.Y.); Philanthropy; Regional planning -- New York (N.Y.); Social problems; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Regional planning; Political science; Psychology; Social sciences; Philanthropic and nonprofit studies; Law
- Russell Sage Foundation records, 1885-1983; 1907-1948; 1; 64.5 Cubic Feet 145 document cases
  Arrangement
  Subgroup 1 of the Russell Sage Foundation records is divided into twelve series:
  1. Mrs. Russell Sage
  2. Corporate History
  3. Early Office Files
  4. General Administration
  5. Programs
  6. Marsh Island
  7. Miscellaneous Reports and Proposals
  8. Nova Institute
  9. "RSF Bulletin"
  10. Personal Giving
  11. Accession 90-76
  1059. Photographs
  Scope and Contents
  The Russell Sage Foundation collection breaks into two distinct categories. Series 1 through Series 9 and Series 11 are the records of the Foundation itself. Series 10 is correspondence from Mrs. Sage's private office documenting her personal giving. Because these letters were given to the Foundation after Mrs. Sage's death in 1918, they have been incorporated into the Russell Sage Foundation Records.
  Although many of the Russell Sage Foundation office files from the early years of the Foundation were systematically destroyed in 1949, all of the early departments are documented to some extent in this collection. Especially well documented are the Charity Organizations/Social Work Administration, the Department of Industrial Studies, and the Southern Highland Division. Particular projects also have extensive records. These include the development of Forest Hills Gardens in Queens; the Foundation's efforts toward the passage of a uniform small loan law; and regional planning, both in the New York City region and in general. The administration of the Russell Sage Foundation during the early period is covered by financial records, agenda and minutes from Board of Trustees meetings, and files on the Russell Sage Foundation Building. Nearly all the material dating from the Foundation's inception to the 1948 reorganization can be found in Series 2 - Corporate History and Series 3 - Early Office Files.
  Of the Russell Sage Foundation's later research programs, those with significant documentation include Government, Law and the Social Sciences; Social Sciences and Human Biology; and Studies in Philanthropy. Records of the administration of the Russell Sage Foundation after 1948 can be found mostly in Series 4 - General Administration.
  The bulk of the material in Series 1 through 9 is correspondence. Much of it concerns routine administrative matters, but a significant portion of the correspondence includes personal opinions of the writers, progress reports, and descriptions of day-by-day activities. Also included are meeting agendas and minutes, progress and annual reports, financial statements, newspaper and magazine clippings, pamphlets and brochures. There is little in the way of field notes or working papers for the Foundation's projects and studies. There are also few personal papers for any department head.
  The correspondence from Mrs. Sage's private office, in Series 10, is mostly incoming letters from organizations and individuals soliciting financial support or advice from Mrs. Sage. Some of the petitioners included in Series 10 have extensive documentation, while others are represented by only a letter or two. In many cases the institutional letters recount the history of the individual organizations. In the process of describing their work and explaining their needs, petitioners requesting Mrs. Sage's support created capsule histories of their institutions.
  Mrs. Sage and her secretaries communicated with one another about the requests by writing on the letters' envelopes, sharing opinions, advice, instructions, and summaries of past actions. Although not all the envelopes have been kept, those that provide insight into Mrs. Sage and those that hold details not expressed in the accompanying letters have been kept. In some cases brief information from the envelope has been transcribed onto the letter as a note in brackets. These notes usually provide the amount of money Mrs. Sage contributed or other action taken concerning the request.
  The letters reflect both the topical and geographic diversity of Mrs. Sage's charitable interests. She was particularly supportive of health care, the welfare of men in the armed forces and merchant marines, religious missions, environmental issues, animal welfare, women's education, and suffrage. Although Mrs. Sage's philanthropic support was international in scope, much of her giving was concentrated in the state of New York. Causes and organizations in Syracuse (her birthplace) and New York City received heavy support. Mrs. Sage was also actively concerned with the needs of Sag Harbor and Lawrence, both Long Island summer residences for her and her husband.
  - Mrs. Russell Sage, 1888-1982, bulk 1907-1917; 1907-1917; 1; 0.88 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
    Scope and Contents note
    This series contains material concerning Mrs. Sage and her personal affairs. It is mostly correspondence relating to several of her personal charities. There is also biographical material and a family genealogy. There is very little correspondence from Mrs. Sage herself. Material on Mr. Russell Sage consists mostly of newspaper and magazine articles about his life and career. Although this material was an integral part of the Foundation's office records and thus is separate from Series 10, which came from Mrs. Sage's personal office, there is some overlap between the two series in the correspondence on Mrs. Sage's personal giving.
    - General, 1907-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - Fitch, 1894, 1909-1918 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
    - Philanthropies - Constitution Island, 1902-1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Philanthropies - Miscellaneous Organizations, 1909-1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Philanthropies - National Association of Audubon Societies, 1910-1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Philanthropies - New York Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor, 1907-1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Philanthropies - New York City Mission and Tract Society, 1888, 1904-1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Philanthropies - New York Exchange for Women's Work, 1903-1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Philanthropies - Salvation Army, 1907-1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Russell Sage, 1894-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Sage, Slocum and Allied Familes" by Wittemore, 1908; 2 copies (Box 1A, Folder 10)
  - Corporate History, 1906-1979; 2; 0.8 Cubic Feet 1.5 boxes
    Arrangement note
    This series is divided into four subseries, as follows:
    Subseries 1: Formation
    Subseries 2: Staff Biographies
    Subseries 3: Trustee Biographies
    Subseries 4: Histories
    - Formation, 1906-1921, 1946-1959, n.d.; 1
      Subseries 1 contains correspondence concerning the earliest function, goals, and direction of the Foundation, as well as the documents of its establishment.
      - Genesis, 1906-1913 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Early Trustee Meetings, 1907-1921 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Letter of Gift, 1907, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Act of Incorporation, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Constitution and Revisions, 1907, 1946-1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Confidential Bulletin Number 1, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Staff Biographies, undated; 2
      Subseries 2 contains biographical information on members of the staff. It is in the form of vitae, memorials, clippings on career achievements, and a few pieces of correspondence.
      - A-L, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - M-Z, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Trustee Biographies, undated; 3
      Subseries 3 contains biographical information on members of the Board of Trustees. It is in the form of vitae, memorials, clippings on career achievements, and a few pieces of correspondence.
      - A-Z, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - General, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Histories, 1915, 1921-1967, 1982; 4
      Subseries 4 contains three drafts and one reprint of histories of the Russell Sage Foundation.
      - Brandt Chronology, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 20a)
      - Brim Draft, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Hammack Draft, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - "Russell Sage Foundation," Schneider, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Photograph Request Correspondence, 1921-1967 (Box 3, Folder 23a)
  - Early Office Files, Bulk, 1907-1949 1907-1980, bulk 1907-1949; 1907-1949; 3; 17.6 Cubic Feet
    The numbering system and the file titles for Series 3 were assigned by the Foundation and have been left intact. The series is arranged by the numbering system. For each file, the designated number is provided in a File Plan note.
    Containing the office files for the Russell Sage Foundation's early period (1907-1949), this series covers the internal administration of the Foundation, the development and functions of its early departments, and the administration of its grants. The material in this series includes correspondence and memoranda; formal and informal activities reports from departments and individuals; financial statements; some minutes of meetings; newspaper clippings, reprints, and brochures. Some of the files are quite extensive while others hold only a piece or two of routine correspondence.
    Russell Sage Foundation Early Office Files Index
    A card index to the Russell Sage Foundation records, Subgroup 1, Series 3: Early Office Files is available for researcher use. RSF Early Office Files are indicated by a file number in the upper right corner of the index cards, ranging from file "1A" to "2212". These file numbers are by the File Plan Notes in this collection guide.
    The RSF Early Office Files Index is located in drawer 64 of the 72-drawer cabinet next to the RAC's reading room.
    - Long Island Railroad YMCA, 1930-1949 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      File Plan note
      1A
      Agreement between RSF and railroad concerning use of station building by YMCA.
    - Mrs. Sage's Estate, 1919-1938 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Settlement of estate.
    - Mrs. Sage's Pensioners, 1919-1945 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      1B
      Pensioners' status and requests.
    - Mrs. Sage's Pensioners, 1919-1945 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Mrs. Sage's Pensioners, 1919-1945 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Clippings about Mrs. Sage's Will, 1920-1927, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      1C
    - DeForest, Johnston, 1932-1949 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      2A
      RSF concerns and activities.
    - DeForest, Robert, 1907-1931 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      2T
      RSF concerns and activities, biographical information.
    - Dodge, Cleveland L., 1909-1920 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      3T
    - White, Alfred T., 1909-1921 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      4T
    - Shepard, Mrs. Finley J. (Helen Gould Shepard), 1928-1936 (Box 4, Folder 34)
      5
    - Finley, John H., 1913-1940 (Box 4, Folder 35)
      6
    - Rice, Mrs. William B., 1907-1926 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      7T
    - Schuyler, Miss Louisa Lee, 1907-1926 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      8T
    - Glenn, John H., 1920-1950 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      9
    - Gillman, Daniel C., 1908 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      10T
      Biographical sketches, including biography published by Johns Hopkins Press.
    - Mrs. Sage's Estate, 1908-1938 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      11
      Legal documents, financial statements.
    - Mrs. Sage's Estate, 1908-1938 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Alton Park, Chattanooga, Tennessee, 1928-1947 (Box 5, Folder 42)
      11A
      Taxes on and sale of property.
    - Gould-Sage Texas Lands, 1928-1950 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      11B
      Administration of land and its sale to Superior Oil Company
    - Gould-Sage Texas Lands, 1928-1950 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Ogden, Robert Curtis, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 45)
      11T
      Biographical sketches.
    - Finances - General, 1907-1921 (Box 5, Folder 46)
      20
      RSF's investments.
    - Finances - General, 1923-1934 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Finances - General, 1935-1939 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Finances - General, 1940-1942 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Finances - General, 1943-1949 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Finances - German Bonds, 1933-1943 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Finances - Proxies, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 52)
      Proxies for RSF.
    - Finances - Resolutions, 1923-1948 (Box 6, Folder 53)
      Approvals for banking transactions.
    - Finances - Review of Investments, 1933-1934 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Finances - Review of Investments, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Finances - Review of Investments, 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Finances - Review of Investments, 1940-1943 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Finances - Review of Investments, 1943-1947 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - New York Trust Company, 1908-1909, 1917-1918 (Box 7, Folder 59)
      20T
      Investment transactions conducted on behalf of RSF.
    - City Housing Corporation - Sunnyside Properties, 1921-1935 (Box 7, Folder 60)
      20.1
      Correspondence, clippings, reports to stockholders. Includes Sunnyside housing strike.
    - City Housing Corporation - Sunnyside Properties, 1921-1935 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - City Housing Corporation - Sunnyside Properties, 1936-1947 (Box 7, Folder 62)
      Correspondence, financial statements.
    - City Housing Corporation - Sunnyside Properties, 1936-1947 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - City Housing Corporation - Sunnyside Properties, 1947-1949 (Box 7, Folder 64)
      Mortgages held by RSF.
    - Finance Committee - General, 1907-1949 (Box 7, Folder 65)
      20.8
      Actions of committee, including management of gift and legacy accounts.
    - Nine Lexington Avenue, 1946-1949 (Box 8, Folder 66)
      20.9
      Purchase of lot by RSF and lot's use.
    - Mortgages, 1933-1948 (Box 8, Folder 67)
      20.11
      Real estate and mortgages owned by RSF.
    - Mortgages, 1933-1948 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Mortgages, 1933-1948 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Mortgages - Coffin - 338-344 Cherry Street, 1933-1952 (Box 8, Folder 70)
      Property mortgaged to RSF by Coffin.
    - Mortgages - Forest Hills, 1931-1947 (Box 8, Folder 71)
      20.13
      Contracts, mortgages and management of Forest Hills Gardens properties. Includes Grosvenor Atterbury correspondence.
    - Mortgages - Forest Hills, 1931-1947 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Mortgages - Miss Todd, 1932-1938 (Box 9, Folder 73)
      20.15
      Mortgage Guarantee Company holdings transferred to RSF by Lilian Todd, Mrs. Sage's personal assistant.
    - New York Title and Mortgage Company, 1932-1948 (Box 9, Folder 74)
      20.16
      Reorganization of New York Title and Mortgage Company; Series F-1 and C-3 investments and investments in Tower Hotel Corp. held by RSF for Sage Institute of Pathology.
    - New York Title and Mortgage Company, 1932-1948 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - New York Title and Mortgage Company, 1932-1948 (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Russell Sage Institute of Pathology - Mortgages, 1933-1947 (Box 9, Folder 77)
      Mortgages held by RSF as trustee for Sage Institute of Pathology.
    - Central Hanover Bank and Trust Co. - Sage Foundation Special Account, 1932-1952 (Box 9, Folder 78)
      20.17
      Correspondence on RSF accounts.
    - Dunbar National Bank, 1931-1938 (Box 9, Folder 79)
      20.21
    - American Power and Light Company (Reorganization), 1947-1954 (Box 9, Folder 80)
      20.22
      RSF investments and reorganization of American Power and Light.
    - National City Bank of New York, 1934-1945 (Box 9, Folder 81)
      Correspondence on RSF Accounts.
    - Corn Exchange Bank, 1945-1948 (Box 9, Folder 82)
      20.23
    - Lord, Clarkson E., 1907-1922 (Box 9, Folder 83)
      30T
      Various RSF accounts and audits. Lord was RSF accountant.
    - DeForest and Elder (Counsel), 1924-1948 (Box 9, Folder 84)
      35
      Financial and legal affairs of RSF.
    - Auditor, 1923-1948 (Box 10, Folder 85)
      35A
      RSF accounting and auditing matters.
    - Executive Committee, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 86)
      51
      Description of Executive Committee in RSF Constitution.
    - Studies in the Professions, 1935-1947 (Box 10, Folder 87)
      61
      Studies of nursing, legal education, legal aid and other topics.
    - Studies in the Professions - Monthly Reports, 1946-1948 (Box 10, Folder 88)
      Project status reports.
    - Susana Hospital, Guam, 1907-1954 (Box 10, Folder 89)
      67A
      Administration of RSF funds and their transfer to Guam Memorial Hospital; design of plaque commemorating Mrs. Sage's gift.
    - Susana Hospital, Guam, 1907-1954 (Box 10, Folder 90)
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building, 1907-1949 (Box 11, Folder 91)
      78
      Building administration, maintenance, and staff matters; value of building and surrounding properties; sale of building to Archbishopric of New York.
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building, 1907-1949 (Box 11, Folder 92)
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building, 1907-1949 (Box 11, Folder 93)
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building (A-F), 1914-1943 (Box 11, Folder 94)
      Administration, maintenance and legal affairs of the RSF Building. Includes addition of west wing.
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building (G-H), 1928-1935 (Box 11, Folder 95)
      Brochures, reprints. Gramercy Park.
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building (I-S), 1915-1951 (Box 11, Folder 96)
      Architecture and physical equipment; symbolic panels; purchase of property for west wing (includes blueprints); sale of building to Archbishopric of New York.
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building (T-U), 1922-1924 (Box 11, Folder 97)
      Construction of 10th story.
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building (V-W), 1928-1932 (Box 11, Folder 98)
      Addition of west wing.
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building - Clayton Smith Management, 1948-1949 (Box 11, Folder 99)
      Management of building by Tankoos, Smith and Company; building operation survey by Clayton Smith.
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building - Employee's Union, 1938-1949 (Box 11, Folder 100)
      Union negotiations and contracts.
    - Russell Sage Foundation Building - Illustrations, undated (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - Russell Sage Foundation Seal, Drawings of, undated (Box 12, Folder 102)
    - National Conference of Social Work - General, 1947-1950 (Box 12, Folder 103)
      79
      RSF membership in Conference and subsidy for writing of Conference history.
    - American Association of Social Workers, 1947-1948 (Box 12, Folder 104)
      108
      Changes in RSF grant policy.
    - Russell Sage Institute of Pathology, 1907-1920 (Box 12, Folder 105)
      130
      Mrs. Sage's endowment, administration of Institute, dispute with Public Charities Commissioner Michael Drummond, affiliation with Bellevue Hospital, financial affairs, research activities.
    - Russell Sage Institute of Pathology, 1907-1920 (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - Russell Sage Institute of Pathology, 1921-1940 (Box 12, Folder 107)
      Administration, financial affairs, research activities.
    - Russell Sage Institute of Pathology, 1940-1958 (Box 12, Folder 108)
      Financial affairs, research activities.
    - Social Work Administration (Formerly Charity Organization), 1929, 1946-1954 (Box 12, Folder 109)
      135
      Publishing activities, suggested study subjects, biographical sketches of Joanna Colcord and Donald Howard.
    - Social Work Administration, 1946-1949 (Box 12, Folder 110)
      Publishing activities, departmental organization and staffing.
    - Social Work Administration - Reports, Clippings, 1946-1949 (Box 12, Folder 111)